We always hear that texting is a scourge.
دائماً ما نسمع أن الرسائل النصية آفة
The idea is that texting spells the decline and fall
والفكرة هي أن الرسائل النصية تعني هبوط وسقوط
of any kind of serious literacy, or at least writing ability,
أي نوع من الأدب الجدي ، او على الاقل القدرة على الكتابة
among young people in the United States
بين شباب الولايات المتحدة
and now the whole world today.
بل و في العالم أجمع
The fact of the matter is that it just isn't true,
في الحقيقة هذا غير صحيح !
and it's easy to think that it is true,
من السهل الإعتقاد أن هذا صحيح
but in order to see it in another way,
ولكن لكي نرى المسألة بطريقة أخرى
in order to see that actually texting is a miraculous thing,
من أجل أن نرى أن الرسائل النصية في الواقع ضرب من الاعجاز
not just energetic, but a miraculous thing,
ليست حيوية فحسب ، و لكن فعلاً معجزة
a kind of emergent complexity
نوع من التعقيد الناشئ
that we're seeing happening right now,
الذي نراه يحدث الآن
we have to pull the camera back for a bit
علينا العودة إلى الوراء بعض الشئ
and look at what language really is,
و النظر الى ماهية اللغة
in which case, one thing that we see
وفي هذه الحالة ، نرى
is that texting is not writing at all.
أن كتابة الرسائل النصية ليست كتابة على الاطلاق
What do I mean by that?
ماذا اعني بذلك ؟
Basically, if we think about language,
أساسياً ، إذا فكرنا في اللغة
language has existed for perhaps 150,000 years,
اللغة موجودة منذ ربما 150,000 سنة
at least 80,000 years,
أو 80,000 سنة على الأقل
and what it arose as is speech. People talked.
و نشأ أولاً الكلام ، تحدث الناس
That's what we're probably genetically specified for.
وهذا غالباً ما حُددنا وراثياً لفعله
That's how we use language most.
هذه كانت طريقتنا الشائعة لإستخدام اللغة
Writing is something that came along much later,
الكتابة أمر أتى في وقت لاحق
and as we saw in the last talk,
وكما رأينا في المحاضرة السابقة
there's a little bit of controversy as to exactly when that happened,
هناك القليل من الجدل عن وقت حدوث هذا بالضبط
but according to traditional estimates,
ولكن وفقاً للتقديرات التقليدية
if humanity had existed for 24 hours,
إذا إفترضنا أن الإنسانية تواجدت لمدة 24 ساعة
then writing only came along at about 11:07 p.m.
فلن تأتي الكتابة إلا حوالى الساعة 11:07 مساءً
That's how much of a latterly thing writing is.
و هذا ما يعبر عن تأخرية الكتابة
So first there's speech, and then writing comes along
إذا أولاً أتى الكلام ، ومن ثم أتت الكتابة
as a kind of artifice.
كنوع من المهارة
Now don't get me wrong, writing has certain advantages.
لا تفهموني خطأ ، للكتابة مزايا معينة
When you write, because it's a conscious process,
عندما تكتب ، لأنها عملية تتطلب الوعي
because you can look backwards,
لأنه بإمكانك النظر إلى الوراء
you can do things with language that are much less likely
يمكنك فعل أشياء باللغة من غير المحتمل تحقيقها
if you're just talking.
إن كنت تتحدث فقط
For example, imagine a passage from Edward Gibbon's
على سبيل المثال، لننظر إلى مقطع من كتاب إدوارد جيبون:
"The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire:"
"تدهور وسقوط الإمبراطورية الرومانية"
"The whole engagement lasted above twelve hours,
" إستمر الاشتباك لأكثر من إثنتي عشرة ساعة
till the graduate retreat of the Persians was changed
حين تحول الإنسحاب التدريجي للفرس
into a disorderly flight, of which the shameful example
الى هروب فوضوي، بسبب المثال المخزي
was given by the principal leaders and the Surenas himself."
الذي قدمه قادتهم الرئيسيين والساريناس أنفسهم "
That's beautiful, but let's face it, nobody talks that way.
هذا جميل، ولكن دعونا نواجه الواقع ، لا أحد يتحدث بهذه الطريقة
Or at least, they shouldn't if they're interested
أو على الأقل ، لا ينبغي أن يتحدث هكذا إن أراد
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
is not the way any human being speaks casually.
هذه ليست طريقة تحدث الإنسان في العادة
Casual speech is something quite different.
الكلام العادي شئ مختلف تماماً
Linguists have actually shown
وقد أظهر اللغويين
that when we're speaking casually in an unmonitored way,
أنه عندما نتحدث طبيعياً بدون رقابة
we tend to speak in word packets of maybe
غالباً نميل إلى الكلام في مجموعات مكونة من
seven to 10 words.
سبعة إلى 10 كلمات
You'll notice this if you ever have occasion to record
سوف تلاحظ هذا إن سبق و قمت بتسجيل
yourself or a group of people talking.
نفسك أو مجموعة من الناس يتحدثون
That's what speech is like.
هكذا يكون الكلام
Speech is much looser. It's much more telegraphic.
الكلام أكثر مرونة و ذو طبيعة تلغرافية
It's much less reflective -- very different from writing.
وهو أقل إنعكاسية ، يختلف جداً عن الكتابة
So we naturally tend to think, because we see language
وطبيعياً نميل إلى الاعتقاد، لأننا نرى اللغة
written so often, that that's what language is,
تكتب في الكثير من الأحيان ، أن هذه ماهية اللغة
but actually what language is, is speech. They are two things.
ولكن في الواقع اللغة و الكلام شيئين مختلفين
Now of course, as history has gone by,
الآن بالطبع ، على مر التاريخ
it's been natural for there to be a certain amount of bleed
من الطبيعي وجود كمية معينة من التداخل
between speech and writing.
بين الكلام والكتابة
So, for example, in a distant era now,
لذا، على سبيل المثال ، في حقبة بعيدة الآن
it was common when one gave a speech
كان من الشائع عندما يلقي أحد خطاباً
to basically talk like writing.
أن يكون حديثه أساساً مثل الكتابة
So I mean the kind of speech that you see someone giving
أنا أعني نوع الخطاب الذي تراه في فيلم قديم
in a certain way which has nothing to do with casual speech.
بطريقة ليس لها علاقة بالحديث غير الرسمي
It's formal. It uses long sentences like this Gibbon one.
بل هو حديث رسمي يستخدم جمل طويلة كالمثال السابق
It's basically talking like you write, and so, for example,
فهو أساسا التحدث مثل الكتابة ، على سبيل المثال
we're thinking so much these days about Lincoln
نحن نفكر كثيراً هذه الأيام بالرئيس لينكولن
because of the movie.
بسبب الفيلم
The Gettysburg Address was not the main meal of that event.
خطاب (جيتيسبيرغ) لم يكن الحدث الأهم
on a topic that, frankly, cannot engage us today
عن موضوع لا يمكنه جذبنا اليوم
and barely did then.
بل و بالكاد جذبنا حينها !
The point of it was to listen to him
المغزى منه كان إلاستماع إليه
speaking like writing.
يتحدث مثل الكتابة
Ordinary people stood and listened to that for two hours.
وقف الناس العاديون واستمعوا إليه لمدة ساعتين
It was perfectly natural.
وكان طبيعياً تماماً
That's what people did then, speaking like writing.
وهذا ما فعله الناس حينها ، التحدث مثل الكتابة
Well, if you can speak like writing,
حسناً ، إن كان بإمكانك التحدث مثل الكتابة
then logically it follows that you might want to also
فأنه من المنطقي أن ترغب في
The problem was just that in the material,
المشكلة أنه من الناحية العملية الميكانيكية
for the simple reason that materials don't lend themselves to it.
للسبب البسيط أنه لم تتواجد الوسائل لفعل ذلك
It's almost impossible to do that with your hand
يكاد يكون مستحيلاً القيام بذلك بيديك
except in shorthand, and then communication is limited.
و بالتالي كان الإتصال محدوداً
On a manual typewriter it was very difficult,
حتى بإستخدام آلة كاتبة يدوية كان صعباً جداً
and even when we had electric typewriters,
وحتى عندما كان لدينا آلات كاتبة كهربائية
or then computer keyboards, the fact is
و لوحة مفاتيح الحاسوب
with the pace of speech, more or less, you have to have
سرعة الكلام، يجب أن يكون لديك
somebody who can receive your message quickly.
شخص ما يمكنه أن يتلقي رسالتك بسرعة
Once you have things in your pocket that can receive that message,
بمجرد أن يكون في جيبك شئ بإمكانه إستقبال هذه الرسالة
then you have the conditions that allow
عندها تكون قد وفرت الظروف التي تسمح لك
And that's where texting comes in.
وهنا تأتي الرسائل النصية !
And so, texting is very loose in its structure.
ولهذا فإن الرسائل النصية فضفاضة في هيكلها
No one thinks about capital letters or punctuation when one texts,
لا أحد يفكر في الإملاء أو علامات الترقيم عند ارسالها
but then again, do you think about those things when you talk?
و مع ذلك ، هل تفكر في هذه الأمور عندما تتكلم ؟
No, and so therefore why would you when you were texting?
لا، و بالتالي لن تفعل عند ما ترسل رسالة نصية
What texting is, despite the fact that it involves
الرسائل النصية، رغم أنها تتضمن
the brute mechanics of something that we call writing,
الدميناميكية الأساسية لشيء نسميه الكتابة
is fingered speech. That's what texting is.
ليست سوى حديث مطبوع
Now we can write the way we talk.
الآن بإمكاننا الكتابة بالطريقة التي نتكلم بها
And it's a very interesting thing, but nevertheless
و إنه لشيء مثير للإهتمام، ولكن
easy to think that still it represents some sort of decline.
من السهل الظن أن الرسائل النصية تمثل نوعاً من التدهور
We see this general bagginess of the structure,
نحن نرى هذا الإسترسال العام في البنية
the lack of concern with rules and the way that we're used to
و عدم الإهتمام بالقواعد والطريقة التي تعودنا عليها
learning on the blackboard, and so we think
و تعلمناها على السبورة ، ولذلك إعتقدنا
that something has gone wrong.
أن خطأ ما قد حدث
It's a very natural sense.
إنه شعور طبيعي جدا.
But the fact of the matter is that what is going on
ولكن حقيقة ما يحدث
That's what we're seeing in this fingered speech.
وهذا ما نراه في هذا الحديث المطبوع
And in order to understand it, what we want to see
ومن أجل فهمه، ما نحتاج إلى رؤيته هو
there is new structure coming up.
حيث يوجد هيكل جديد يبني
as meaning "laughing out loud."
تعني "الضحك بصوت عالي."
And of course, theoretically, it does,
وهذا صحيح من الناحية النظرية،
and if you look at older texts, then people used it
وإذا نظرتم إلى النصوص القديمة، استخدمها الناس آنذاك
to actually indicate laughing out loud.
للإشارة إلى ضحكهم بصوت عال.
is aware of the substrate of texting the way it's become,
على علم بالطريقة التي أصبحت عليها الرسائل النصية،
you'll notice that LOL
ستلاحظ أن "LOL"
It's evolved into something that is much subtler.
لقد تطورت إلى شي أقل حدة
This is an actual text that was done
هذا نص فعلي كتبه
not too long ago.
منذ فترة غير بعيدة
"I love the font you're using, btw."
"بالمناسبة، أحب نوع الخط الذي تستخدمين."
Julie: "lol thanks gmail is being slow right now"
جولي: "LOL" شكرا الإيميل بطيء الآن"
Now if you think about it, that's not funny.
إذا فكرت في الأمر، فالأمر ليس مضحكا.
No one's laughing. (Laughter)
لا أحد يضحك. (ضحك)
And yet, there it is, so you assume
ومع ذلك، قد كتبت، فتفترض
there's been some kind of hiccup.
إن هناك نوع من الخطأ
Then Susan says "lol, I know,"
ثم تقول سوزان "LOL، أنا أعلم،"
again more guffawing than we're used to
ومرة أخرى المزيد من الضحك أكثر من المعتاد
when you're talking about these inconveniences.
عندما نتحدث عن مثل هذه المضايقات.
So Julie says, "I just sent you an email."
حيث تقول جولي، "أقد أرسلت لك ببريد للتو"
Susan: "lol, I see it."
سوزان: "لول، أنا أراها".
Very funny people, if that's what LOL means.
أناس مضحكون جدا، إذا كان هذا معنى "LOL".
Susan: "lol, I have to write a 10 page paper."
سوزان: "لول، علي كتابة تقرير من 10 صفحات."
She's not amused. Let's think about it.
هي لم تتسلى بالأمر. دعونا نفكر في ذلك.
LOL is being used in a very particular way.
لقد تم استخدام LOL بطريقة خاصة جدا
It's a marker of empathy. It's a marker of accommodation.
هي علامة على التعاطف. هي علامة على المجاملة
We linguists call things like that pragmatic particles.
نحن اللغويون نسمي هذه الأشياء بالأدوات العملية.
Any spoken language that's used by real people has them.
توجد هذه الأدوات في أي لغة يستخدمها أناس حقيقيون.
If you happen to speak Japanese, think about
إذا حدث وكنت تتحدث اليابانية، فكر في
that little word "ne" that you use at the end of a lot of sentences.
الكلمة الصغيرة "ne" اللتي تستخدمها في نهاية الكثير من الجمل
If you listen to the way black youth today speak,
إذا استمعت إلى الطريقة التي يتحدث بها الشباب الزنوج،
Whole dissertations could be written about it,
يمكن كتابة اطروحات كاملة عنها،
and probably are being written about it.
وغالبا ما تكتب الآن عنها.
A pragmatic particle, that's what LOL has gradually become.
قد أصبحت "LOL" تدريجيا أداة عملية.
It's a way of using the language between actual people.
إنها طريقة لإستخدام اللغة بين الناس الفعليين.
Another example is "slash."
مثال آخر هو " / "
Now, we can use slash in the way that we're used to,
الآن، يمكننا استخدام "سلاش" ( / ) بالطريقة التي اعتدنا عليها،
along the lines of, "We're going to have
على غرار، "سنقيم
a party-slash-networking session."
حفل / جلسة تواصل
That's kind of like what we're at.
هذا ما نحن عليه الآن
Slash is used in a very different way
تستخدم " / " بطريقة مختلفة جدا
in texting among young people today.
في الرسائل النصية بين الشباب اليوم.
It's used to change the scene.
إنها تستخدم لتغيير المشهد.
So for example, this Sally person says,
على سبيل المثال، تقول سالي
"So I need to find people to chill with"
"أحتاج الى أناس لأتسكع معهم"
and Jake says, "Haha" --
ويقول جيك، "هاها"-
you could write a dissertation about "Haha" too, but we don't have time for that —
ــــ يمكنك كتابة أطروحة عن "هاها" أيضا، ولكن ليس لدينا وقتا لذلك ــــــ
"Haha so you're going by yourself? Why?"
"هاها تريدين الذهاب بمفردك؟ لماذا؟ "
Sally: "For this summer program at NYU."
سالي: "لبرنامج صيفي في جامعة نيويورك."
Jake: "Haha. Slash I'm watching this video with suns players
جيك: "هاها / كنت أشاهد هذا الفيديو مع لاعبي صنز
trying to shoot with one eye."
يحاولون إطلاق النار بعين واحدة ".
The slash is interesting.
إن الـ" / " مثيرة للإهتمام.
I don't really even know what Jake is talking about after that,
حقيقة لا أعرف حتى ما يتكلم عنه جيك بعدها،
but you notice that he's changing the topic.
لكنك تلاحظ أنه يغير الموضوع.
Now that seems kind of mundane,
يبدو هذا بسيط،
but think about how in real life,
لكن فكر في الأمر في الحياة الواقعية،
if we're having a conversation and we want to change the topic,
إذا كنا في حوار ونريد تغيير الموضوع،
there are ways of doing it gracefully.
هناك طرقٌ للقيام بذلك بطريقة لبقة.
You don't just zip right into it.
لن تغير الموضوع بصورة مباشرة.
You'll pat your thighs and look wistfully off into the distance,
سوف تطبطب فخذيك وتنظر إلى الأفق،
or you'll say something like, "Hmm, makes you think --"
أو ستقول شيئا مثل، "هممم، ذلك يذكرك بـ ـــ ـــ "
when it really didn't, but what you're really --
عندما لم يذكرك بشيء، ولكن ما ــ
(Laughter) —
(ضحك) ـــــــ
You can't do that while you're texting,
لكن لا يمكنك فعل ذلك خلال الرسائل النصية،
and so ways are developing of doing it within this medium.
لذا فالطرق تتطور للقيام بذلك بواسطة هذا الرمز
All spoken languages have what a linguist calls
جميع اللغات المنطوقة لها ما يسميه لغوي
a new information marker -- or two, or three.
علامة معلومات جديدة-أو اثنين أو ثلاثة.
Texting has developed one from this slash.
الرسائل النصية وقد وضعت واحدة من هذه الـ " / ".
So we have a whole battery of new constructions
لذا لدينا بطارية كاملة للإنشاءات الجديدة
that are developing, and yet it's easy to think,
التي تتطور، وحتى الآن فمن السهل أن يفكر،
well, something is still wrong.
حسنا، لا يزال هناك شيءٌ خاطئ.
There's a lack of structure of some sort.
هناك نوعٌ من ضعف في الهيكلية .
It's not as sophisticated
أنها ليست متطورة كما
as the language of The Wall Street Journal.
كاللغة في "صحيفة وول ستريت جورنال".
Well, the fact of the matter is,
حسنا، حقيقة الأمر،
look at this person in 1956,
انظروا إلى هذا الشخص في عام 1956،
and this is when texting doesn't exist,
وهذا عندما لم يكن للرسائل النصية وجود ،
"I Love Lucy" is still on the air.
"أنا لوسي الحب" لا يزال على الهواء.
"Many do not know the alphabet or multiplication table,
"كثيرون لا يعرفون الحروف الأبجدية أو جدول الضرب،
cannot write grammatically -- "
لا يمكن كتابة نحوياً "
We've heard that sort of thing before,
لقد سمعنا شيئاً من هذا النوع من قبل،
not just in 1956. 1917, Connecticut schoolteacher.
ليس فقط في عام 1956. عام 1917، أستاذ مدرسة في كونيتيكت .
1917. This is the time when we all assume
1917. هذا العام الذي نفترض جميعاً
that everything somehow in terms of writing was perfect
أن الأشياء المتعلقة بالكتابة كانت مثالية .
because the people on "Downton Abbey" are articulate,
لأن الناس في "دير داونتون" كانو فصيحين،
or something like that.
أو شيء من هذا القبيل.
So, "From every college in the country goes up the cry,
لذا، "من كل كلية في البلاد ترتفع الصرخة،
'Our freshmen can't spell, can't punctuate.'"
"طلاب السنة الأولى لا يمكنهم أن يهجؤوا أو يلفظوا .'"
And so on. You can go even further back than this.
وهلم جرا. يمكنك العودة أبعد من ذلك .
It's the President of Harvard. It's 1871.
هاك رئيس لجامعة هارفارد. في عام 1871.
There's no electricity. People have three names.
وهناك لا كهرباء. الناس لديهم ثلاثة أسماء.
"Bad spelling,
"التهجئة الخاطئة ،
incorrectness as well as inelegance of expression in writing."
الخطأ ، واللا أناقة في التعبير في الكتابة "
And he's talking about people who are otherwise
ويتحدث عن الناس الذين هم على خلاف ذلك
well prepared for college studies.
معدين جيدا للدراسة في الجامعة.
You can go even further back.
يمكنك الذهاب أبعد من ذلك مرة أخرى.
1841, some long-lost superintendent of schools is upset
1841 مراقب مدرسة ذو خبرة منزعج
because of what he has for a long time "noted with regret
بسبب ما لاحظه منذ فترة طويلة من الزمن "ولاحظت مع الأسف
the almost entire neglect of the original" blah blah blah blah blah.
الإهمال الشبه كلي للـ ........... إلخ ".
Or you can go all the way back to 63 A.D. -- (Laughter) --
أو يمكنك أن تعود كل تلك السنين إلى سنة 63 للميلاد-(ضحك)-
and there's this poor man who doesn't like the way
ويوجد هذا الرجل الفقير الذي لا يحب الطريقة
people are speaking Latin.
الناس يتحدثون اللاتينية.
As it happens, he was writing about what had become French.
وكما تبين أنه كان يكتب عما أصبح بعد ذلك "الفرنسية"
And so, there are always — (Laughter) (Applause) —
وهكذا، هناك دائماً--(ضحك) (تصفيق) –
there are always people worrying about these things
هناك دائماً من الناس من يقلق بشأن هذه الأمور
and the planet somehow seems to keep spinning.
وكوكبنا يحافظ على دورانه بشكل ما .
And so, the way I'm thinking of texting these days is
إذاً ، الطريقة التي أنظر فيها إلى الرسائل النصية هذه الأيام
that what we're seeing is a whole new way of writing
أن ما نراه طريقة جديدة كاملة للكتابة
that young people are developing,
يطورها الشباب
which they're using alongside their ordinary writing skills,
والتي يستخدمونها إلى جانب مهاراتهم الكتابية العادية
and that means that they're able to do two things.
وهذا يعني أنهم قادرين على القيام بأمرين.
Increasing evidence is that being bilingual
الدليل المؤكد هو أن كونك تتحدث لغتين
is cognitively beneficial.
فهو أمر مفيد معرفيا,
That's also true of being bidialectal.
وهذا أيضا صحيح إذا ماكنت تتحدث بلكنتين.
That's certainly true of being bidialectal in terms of your writing.
وهذا صحيح أيضاً إذا ما كنت مزدوج اللكنة من حيث الكتابة الخاصة بك.
And so texting actually is evidence of a balancing act
فالرسائل النصية في الواقع هي دليل على الموازنة
that young people are using today, not consciously, of course,
التي يستخدمها الشباب ، عن غير وعي، بالطبع،
but it's an expansion of their linguistic repertoire.
ولكنها تعد توسيعاً لذخيرتهم اللغوية.
It's very simple.
إن الأمر بسيط جداً .
If somebody from 1973 looked at
إذا ما نظر شخص ما من عام 1973 إلى
what was on a dormitory message board in 1993,
ما كان في غرفة مجلس مناقشة رسالة في عام 1993،
the slang would have changed a little bit
تغيرت العامية قليلاً
since the era of "Love Story,"
ومنذ عصر "قصة حب"،
but they would understand what was on that message board.
ولكنهم كانوا ليفهموا ما كان في ذلك المجلس.
Take that person from 1993 -- not that long ago,
خذ هذا الشخص من 1993-ليس ذلك منذ فترة طويلة،
this is "Bill and Ted's Excellent Adventure" -- those people.
هذا هو "بيل وتيد الممتازة مغامرة"-هؤلاء الناس.
Take those people and they read
قم بأخذ هؤلاء الناس وهم يقرأون
a very typical text written by a 20-year-old today.
نصاً نموذجياً جداً كتبه شخص بعمرالـعشرين سنة اليوم.
Often they would have no idea what half of it meant
غالباً لن يفهموا ما يعنيه نصف النص .
because a whole new language has developed
لأن لغة جديدة كاملة قد وضعت
among our young people doing something as mundane
بين شبابنا وهم يقومون بشيء بسيط
as what it looks like to us when they're batting around
وفق ما يبدو لنا وهم يقومون بالنقر
on their little devices.
على الأجهزة الصغيرة الخاصة بهم .
So in closing, if I could go into the future,
لذا في الختام، إذا تمكنت من السفر إلى المستقبل،
if I could go into 2033,
إذا تمكنت من الذهاب إلى عام 2033،
the first thing I would ask is whether David Simon
أول شيء أود أن اسأل عنه ما إذا كان ديفيد سيمون
had done a sequel to "The Wire." I would want to know.
قد مثل جزءاً ثانياً من "السلك". أريد أن أعرف ذلك.
And — I really would ask that —
حقاً سوف أسأل عن هذا .
and then I'd want to know actually what was going on on "Downton Abbey."
وثم أريد أن أعرف فعلا ما كان يجري "دير داونتون".
That'd be the second thing.
ذاك سيكون الشيء الثاني
And then the third thing would be,
وبعدها الشيء الثالث سيكون،
please show me a sheaf of texts
رجاءً أعطوني ورقة تحتوي نص
written by 16-year-old girls,
كتبت من قبل فتيات في السادسة عشر من العمر،
because I would want to know where this language
لأن أريد أن أعرف إلى أين وصل تطور لغتنا
had developed since our times,
منذ عصرنا
and ideally I would then send them back to you and me now
ومن الناحية المثالية سوف أرسلها إليكم وإلي هنا
so we could examine this linguistic miracle
لكي يمكننا أن نرى هذه المعجزة اللغوية
happening right under our noses.
التي تحدث أمامنا .
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا. (تصفيق)